Finding Aid for the Joseph Gaer Papers LSC.0379
UCLA Library Special Collections
Joseph Gaer papers
1934-1957
UCLA Library Special Collections
Gaer, Joseph
LSC.0379
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Joseph Gaer (originally Joseph Fishman) (1897-1969) was a lecturer in contemporary literature at UC Berkeley (1930-35), editor-in-chief and chief field supervisor for the Federal Writers Project (1935-39), consultant to the administrator of the Farm Security Administration (1939-41), special assistant to Secretary of the Treasury (1941-43), publicity director of the Political Action Committee for the Congress of Industrial Organizations (1943-45), founder and director of Pamphlet Press (1945-46), and president of Boni & Gaer (later Gaer Associates Publishing Company) (1946-49). He also wrote many books, including The legend called Meryon (1928), and Our Jewish heritage (1957). The collection consists of manuscripts of books written or edited by Joseph Gaer, and includes typescripts with holograph corrections and corrected galley and page proofs.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joseph Gaer, 1953-58.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9914704663606533
Biography
Joseph Gaer (originally Joseph Fishman) was born March 16, 1897 in Yedinitz, Russia; came to U.S., 1917; attended colleges in the U.S. and Canada; lecturer in contemporary literature, UC Berkeley, 1930-35; editor-in-chief and chief field supervisor, Federal Writers Project, 1935-39; consultant to administrator of Farm Security Administration, 1939-41; special assistant to Secretary of the Treasury, 1941-43; publicity director of Political Action Committee, Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1943-45; founder and director of Pamphlet Press, 1945-46; president, Boni & Gaer (later Gaer Associates Publishing Company), 1946-49; in 1958 became founder and director of Jewish Heritage Foundation, Beverly Hills; wrote many books, including The legend called Meryon (1928), How the great religions began (1929), and Our Jewish heritage (1957); died December 7, 1969.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of manuscripts of books written or edited by Joseph Gaer. Includes typescripts with holograph corrections and corrected galley and page proofs.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Modern family Bible (Box 1).
The adventure of Rama, Jack London, The lore of the New Testament (Box 2).
The fables of India, Holidays around the world, Young heroes of the living religions (Box 3).
Holidays around the world (corrected proofs), The wisdom of living religions (Box 4).
Our Jewish heritage (Box 5).
General note
Description derived from in-house card files.
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Jewish authors -- 20th century -- Archives.; Manuscripts for publication; Gaer, Joseph, 1897-1969--Archives.
- Modern family Bible, O.T. and N.T. edited by and annotated by Joseph Gaer and Chester C. McCown. Santa Monica, 8 parts in 4. "Prefinal draft" Multilith process. Some corrections in ink. (Box 1)
- The adventures of Rama. The story of the great Hindu epic Ramayana. Santa Monica, First published by Little, Brown, Boston, n.d. 1954.; 259, 10 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 2)
  General note
  Gift of the author, 11-10-1954.
- Jack London, bibliography, biographical data and index of works. From California State Emergency Relief Administration's California Literary Research Monographs no.1. [n.p., ]., 1934; 45 leaves. Typescript. (Box 2)
- The lore of the New Testament. n.p., First published by Little, Brown, Boston, n.d. 1952.; 622, 41 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. Book jacket included. In brown binder. (Box 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Gift of the author, May 11, 1953.
- The fables of India. Illustrated by Randy Monk. n.p., First published by Little, Brown, Boston, n.d. 1955.; Typescript with holograph corrections. 263 leaves (Box 3)
  Gift of the author, October 1955.
- Holidays around the world. New York, 244, [18] leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections in 2 folders. (Box 3)
  Gift of the author, May 1953.
  - Also: corrected galley proofs. First published by Little, Brown, Boston, 1953.; 68 sheets. Book jacket included. (Box 4)
- Young heroes of the living religions. n.p., First published by Little, Brown, Boston, n.d. 1953.; 244, [19] leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 3)
  Gift of the author, November 1953.
- The wisdom of living religions. n.p., n.d.; ca. 300 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 4)
  - Also: 1. corrected galley proofs. First published by Dodd, Mead, New York, 1956.; 77 sheets. 2. corrected page proofs. 324 pages. (Box 4)
    Gift of the author, November 1956.
- Our Jewish heritage by Joseph Gaer and Alfred Wolf. n.p., 1957.; xv, 317, 30 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 4)
  - Also: 1. corrected galley proofs. First published by Henry Holt, New York, 1957.; 77 sheets. 2. corrected page proofs. 234pp. (Box 4)
    Gift of the author, April 1958.